<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry>

<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>tfortune</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv id="name">
<refname>tfortune</refname>
<refpurpose>fortune with recursive directory traversal</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv id="synopsis">
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>tfortune</command>
<arg choice="opt">-c</arg>
<arg choice="opt">-e</arg>
<arg choice="opt">-f</arg>
<arg choice="opt">-w</arg>
<!--
<arg choice="opt">-n <replaceable>width</replaceable></arg>
-->
<arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">path</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'>
<title>Description</title>
<para>
<command>tfortune</command> samples a random fortune cookie (or other snippet of text) from text files in
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
format, and writes it to standard output.
<command>tfortune</command> is a partial reimplementation of
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
that adds the feature of recursive directory traversal; <command>tfortune</command> scours an entire directory hierarchy for text files from which to sample. The user may specify an alternative directory hierarchy to search by giving its <replaceable>path</replaceable> as an argument.
</para>
<variablelist remap="IP">
<varlistentry>
<term><option>-c</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>Write not only the cookie but also its file of origin.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><option>-e</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>Give every fortune cookie file an equal chance of being sampled from, regardless of size (instead of choosing a file with probability proportional to the number of fortunes it has).</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><option>-f</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>Instead of displaying a fortune cookie, list the files from which one would've been sampled, along with each file's chance of being chosen.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><option>-w</option></term>
<listitem>
<para>Give the user time to read the written cookie by waiting for a bit before exiting. (Slower readers may repeat this option to extend the waiting time.)</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
By default <command>tfortune</command> interprets <replaceable>path</replaceable> as a directory, but <replaceable>path</replaceable> may be a regular file, in which case <command>tfortune</command> presumes it to be a fortune cookie file it should add to its list.
</para>
</refsect1>

<para>
Given the <option>-c</option> option, <command>tfortune</command>'s writes the sampled file's full path, unlike
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>,
which writes only the file's name.
Because <command>tfortune</command> may scan multiple directories, a file's name alone may not uniquely identify it, and if so mimicking
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>'s
behaviour would introduce ambiguity. For the same reason, when given only a file name as an argument, <command>tfortune</command> treats it like any other path &mdash; if the file isn't found, <command>tfortune</command> does not try to locate the file in the default fortune cookie directories as
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
does.
</para>

<para>
With the <option>-w</option> option, <command>tfortune</command> decides on a waiting time in a more sophisticated way than
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>,
which pauses for a time proportional to the number of bytes in the fortune cookie (leading to inordinately long waits if the fortune cookie is ASCII art).
</para>

<refsect1 id="limitations">
<title>Limitations</title>

<para>
Where <command>tfortune</command> implements features of 
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>,
<command>tfortune</command> tries to mimic its behaviour if that's sensible, but there are some differences, and most options
(<option>-a</option>, <option>-i</option>, <option>-l</option>, <option>-m</option>, <option>-n</option>, <option>-o</option>, <option>-s</option> and <option>-u</option>)
are simply unimplemented.
</para>

<para>
<command>tfortune</command> does not recognize
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>'s
(inevitably somewhat arbitrary) distinction between offensive and inoffensive fortune cookies, and is content to sample from any and all compatible files it finds.
<command>tfortune</command> also does not understand percentage arguments
(which
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
interprets as selection probabilities for a subsequent file name argument) &mdash; it just treats them as file names.
</para>

<para>
If <command>tfortune</command> comes across a valid file multiple times, it dutifully adds the file repeatedly to its list.
<command>tfortune</command> does not check for duplicates on its list of files from which to sample, on the assumption that if the user tells the program to traverse a directory twice or to record a file twice, the user knows what they're doing.
</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="author">
<title>Author</title>
<para>Written by Drew Thomas.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="copyright">
<title>Copyright</title>
<para>Both <command>tfortune</command> and this documentation are public domain; the author disclaims all copyright.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="seealso">
<title>See also</title>
<para>
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>fortune</refentrytitle><manvolnum>6</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>,
<citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>strfile</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
